Finding Aid for Nu Sigma Nu, Alpha Chapter. (University of Michigan) records, 1882-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Nu Sigma Nu, Alpha Chapter. (University of Michigan) records 1882-1999
Nu Sigma Nu, Alpha Chapter. (University of Michigan)
22 oversize folders
8 linear feet
2008137 Bimu F 41 2
The Nu Sigma Nu Fraternity was founded at the University of Michigan in 1882 and is the oldest medical fraternity in the United States. It was created to promote cooperation and fellowship among medical men and to raise medical education and scholarship to a higher level. These records document the creation of the Nu Sigma Nu fraternity and the history of the Alpha Chapter from its inception in 1882 to its termination in 2008.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records received in 1989 and 2008 (Donor # 7811 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
The Nu Sigma Nu medical fraternity is the oldest medical fraternity in the United States. It was formally established in 1882 at the University of Michigan in Ann Arbor by six medical students: Frederick Clark Bailey, Charles Marshall Frye, John Lincoln Gish, William James Mayo, Robert D. Stephens, and Benjamin Grinnell Strong. The Grand Chapter (later the Grand Council) was formed in 1886, making Nu Sigma Nu a national organization. Articles of incorporation were filed in 1896. At its peak in the late 1940s, Nu Sigma Nu had local chapters at over 40 universities throughout the United States and Canada.
The Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu had two official chapter houses during its existence at the University of Michigan. Before the construction of the first chapter house, Nu Sigma Nu members lived in seven different rented locations around campus. The idea for the first official chapter house was conceived in 1895 using land at the site of 1015 East Huron Avenue. The property was purchased in 1902. Active members of the Alpha Chapter each pledged $125 to support the construction of the house, while faculty members of the fraternity subscribed $1,725. A loan was secured to cover the remaining costs, with subscriptions put toward the eventual repayment of the loan. The total cost of the house was $17,000. Construction began in 1905 and the Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu moved into the house in April 1907.
After more than 50 years on East Huron, the Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu moved to a new location, on property owned and operated by the University of Michigan, at 1912 Geddes Avenue. A campaign to create and build a second chapter house began around 1958 and continued through 1969. Nu Sigma Nu alumni contributed a total of $270,000 to the Nu Sigma Nu Building Fund; the remaining $105,000 was loaned to the fraternity by the University of Michigan and paid back in the 1970s. Nu Sigma Nu members moved into the new house in the fall of 1970 and occupied it until 2008.
After a peak in fraternal spirit and enthusiasm in the 1940s and 50s, both the national organization and the local chapter of Nu Sigma N experienced a decline in enrollment. The national organization disbanded in the 1970s following the termination of several chapters. The Alpha Chapter maintained its presence at the University of Michigan but a disagreement with the Housing Division of the University of Michigan in 1986 revealed that the Alpha Chapter had, ten years earlier, lost its non-profit corporation status as well as violated the terms of its lease with the University. This revelation resulted in the members of Nu Sigma Nu banding together with renewed purpose. They concentrated their efforts on hosting more frequent alumni gatherings, publishing bulletins and announcements more regularly, and establishing a scholarship fund that enabled fourth-year medical students to complete a rotation abroad in an underprivileged area of the world. The most obvious sign of their efforts was the 1990 All-Year Reunion that brought Nu Sigma Nu alumni back to Ann Arbor from all parts of the country. Despite this surge in fraternal activity, the Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu experienced further decline and eventually disbanded in 2008.
The Nu Sigma Nu, Alpha Chapter collection contains records that relate to both the local chapter of Nu Sigma Nu as well as the founding of the national organization. Information within these records reveals the history of the fraternity, the daily business of the Alpha Chapter throughout its existence, and the interaction between the Alpha Chapter and the University of Michigan. These records are divided into eight series: Administration, Correspondence, Financial Records, History, Housing, Nu Sigma Nu Medical Scholarship Fund, Photographs, and Publications.
Subjects:
Novy, Frederick George, 1864-1957.; Greek letter societies--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Nu Sigma Nu. Alpha Chapter (University of Michigan); University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan--Students--Societies, etc.
- Administration
  The Administration series contains five subseries, as well as other topical files pertaining to the day-to-day business of the fraternity. These subseries are: Constitutions and Manuals, Events, Fraternities, House Business, and Legal. Within them are records pertaining to specific events and actions in the life of the Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu as well as general announcements made to members the national fraternity. Specifically, the subseries Events, House Business, and Legal contain records that pertain only to the Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu at the University of Michigan. The subseries Constitutions and Manuals contains publications or letters that pertain to all chapters of the national fraternity.
  - Alumni Lists (Box 1)
  - Disciplinary Actions 1909-1967 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions and Manuals
    - Constitution & Manual, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Constitution of the Inter-Professional Fraternity Conference undated (Box 1)
    - Constitution of the Nu Sigma Nu Fraternity, undated (Box 1)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Constitution Reminders circa 1960-1968 (Box 1)
    - Ritual for Initiation of New Members, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Events
    - 1990 All-Year Reunion
      - Alumni Reunion Book Responses (Box 1)
      - Follow-up Correspondence (Box 1)
      - Planning (Box 1)
    - Computer Kickoff 1987-1991 (Box 1)
    - Gatherings 1984-1988 (Box 1)
    - Guest Sign-in Book 1986-1990 (Box 1)
    - Invitations 1905-1999 (Box 1)
  - Fraternities
    - Chapters of Nu Sigma Nu throughout the U.S. 1903, 1923, 1970 (Box 1)
    - Others at University of Michigan 1914-1922 (Box 1)
  - House Business
    - House Rules circa 1960s-1974 (Box 1)
    - House Rules and Correspondence 1981-1989 (Box 1)
    - House Rules and Correspondence 1990-1999 (Box 1)
  - Initiation Certificates (1918-1965) (Box 1)
  - Legal
    - Non-Profit Corporation Status 1952-1987 (Box 1)
    - Resident Agent 1947-1989 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous 1954-1986 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Minutes 1914-1999 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series contains six subseries: Alumni Correspondence, Building Correspondence, Executive Council Correspondence, Fraternity Business, Officer Correspondence, and University of Michigan Housing Division Correspondence. Records within these subseries that are enclosed in titled folders are arranged alphabetically by subject; all other documents are arranged chronologically. The Alumni Correspondence subseries contains letters sent either to or from Alpha Chapter alumni during the time periods listed. The subject matter of these letters is usually personal and not related to the subjects of the other subseries. The Building Correspondence subseries contains records that relate to two separate periods of construction in the history of the Alpha Chapter: the construction of its first chapter house, in 1906, and the restoration of that house in the 1960s. The Executive Council Correspondence subseries contains two folders that overlap chronologically. The Fraternity Business subseries contains correspondence that pertains to both the Alpha Chapter (also known as the Nu Sigma Nu Corporation) and the national organization of Nu Sigma Nu.
  The Officer Correspondence subseries contains the correspondence of several key people within the Nu Sigma Nu fraternity, either nationally or locally. The files are arranged alphabetically by the last name of the officer (or by one of the officers, if it contains more than one person). The subject matter of these correspondence is far-reaching and varied, ranging from the construction of the first chapter house to collecting house dues to managing the affairs of the national organization. Some of the officers' correspondence is still housed within their original filing system. Of particular interest is the correspondence of Frederick G. Novy, who served as Secretary for the Corporation of the Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu for several years. One set of correspondence was taken directly from Dr. Novy's own filing system and dates from 1902 to 1913. Additional correspondence of Dr. Novy is organized chronologically from 1911 to 1923. The subseries University of Michigan Housing Division Correspondence contains one folder of general correspondence and one folder pertaining to a 1986 incident that called into question the legal status of the Nu Sigma Nu Corporation and the ownership of the Alpha Chapter house.
  - Alumni Correspondence
    - 1974-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1989-1991 (Box 1)
  - Building Correspondence
    - Building Fund 1962-1963 (Box 1)
    - Campfield Construction Company 1906-1907 (Box 1)
  - Executive Council Correspondence
    - 1919-1924 (Box 1)
    - 1922-1924 (Box 1)
  - Fraternity Business
    - Inter-fraternity Council 1956-1961 (Box 1)
    - Intra-fraternity Correspondence 1968-2003 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence 1900-1943 (Box 1)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Corporation Correspondence 1959-1973 (Box 1)
  - Officer Correspondence
    - Paul S. Barker and Malcolm H. Soule, Secretary-Treasurers of Nu Sigma Nu 1948-1956 (Box 1)
    - A. R. Buchanan and George H. Lowrey, Executive Council Members 1962-1969 (Box 1)
    - L. M. Gelston, Officer of Nu Sigma Nu, Alpha Chapter 1904-1905 (Box 1)
    - Frederick G. Novy, Secretary for the Corporation of the Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu 1902-1913, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Frederick G. Novy, Secretary for the Corporation of the Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu 1911-1923 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Housing Division Correspondence
    - General correspondence 1970-1991, 2002 (Box 2)
    - Issue Concerning Renting the House to Other Student Organizations 1985-1986 (Box 2)
- Financial Records
  The Financial Records series includes two main files: Account Books and Monthly Balance Sheets. Within the Account Books file are various record books belonging to the Nu Sigma Nu Corporation or house officers. Of particular note is the Record Book for Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu, dating back to 1895, in which some of the earliest members of Nu Sigma Nu pledged money to build the first chapter house. Also within that book are records of house dues over several decades, expense listings, meeting announcements, and letters from then-active members. The file Monthly Balance Sheets contains two folders of detailed financial records for the Alpha Chapter house, ranging from 1949 to 1996.
  - Account Books
    - Bank Books 1906-1948, 1963-1970 (Box 2)
    - Duplicating Book of Treasurer of Nu Sigma Nu 1904 (Box 2)
    - Financial Record Books 1982-1983, 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - Record Book for Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu 1895-1962 (contains list of members' subscriptions, plus announcements and meetings, mostly financial, some administrative) (Box 2)
  - Alumni Donation Records for $55 Million Program circa 1966 (Box 2)
  - Budgets/Treasury Reports 1970-2001 (Box 2)
  - General Financial Correspondence 1887-1925 (Box 2)
  - Monthly Balance Sheets
    - 1949-1960 (Box 2)
    - 1961-1967 (Box 2)
    - 1982-1996 (Box 2)
  - Nu Sigma Nu House Fund 1950-1969 (Box 2)
- History
  The History series contains one record book, created around 1905, in which Nu Sigma Nu Alpha Chapter members of early years would eventually write their autobiographies. Although it is only partially completed, the book contains pages of autobiographical information about Nu Sigma Nu men and their careers in medicine. A separate folder within that file contains non-dated historical information about the founding and development of the fraternity in general, presumably written for publication in annual bulletins or alumni newsletters. In addition to written documents, there exist two artifacts within the History series: the original charter from 1882 and the crest of Nu Sigma Nu.
  - Alpha of Nu Sigma Nu Chapter History 1905-1941 (Box 2)
  - Historical Accounts of Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu circa 1960s-1997 (Box 2)
  - Artifacts
    - Original Charter of Alpha Chapter, Nu Sigma Nu 1882 (Folder Bimu)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Crest (Folder Bimu)
- Housing
  The Housing series contains two subseries: 1906 House (1015 E. Huron) and 1969 House (1912 Geddes). There have been two permanent chapter houses of the Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu: the house built at 1015 East Huron Avenue in 1906 and the house built at 1912 Geddes Avenue in 1969. Within the subseries 1906 House (1015 E. Huron) there exist legal documents, insurance policies taken out for the house, and a record of house inspections done by the Housing Division of the University of Michigan. Information pertaining to the construction of the 1906 house can be found in the Correspondence series, in the subseries Building Correspondence. The subseries 1969 House (1912 Geddes) contains similar records, as well as information on the campaign to build the second chapter house, how the house was furnished, and individual incidents that occurred while the house was in use. Financial documents relating to the houses can be found in the series Financial Records.
  - 1906 House (1015 E. Huron) (Box 3)
    - Contracts 1896-1907 (Box 3)
    - Inspections 1951-1968 (Box 3)
    - Insurance Policies 1907-1961 (Box 3)
    - Legal Papers (Mortgage, Title, Lease Agreements) 1894-1920 (Box 3)
  - 1969 House (1912 Geddes)
    - Blueprints 1969 (Box 3)
    - Campaign to Build New Chapter House 1956-1970 (Box 3)
    - Furnishings
      - Donations to Home Furnishing Fund 1970 (Box 3)
      - Furnishing Budgets and Inventories 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    - Inspections 1967-1991 (Box 3)
    - Insurance Policies and Documentation 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    - Lease Agreements 1965-1971 (Box 3)
    - Oxford Housing Parking Dispute 1986 (Box 3)
    - Potential Sale of House to Telluride 1999 (Box 3)
    - Repairs/Improvements 1972-1991 (Box 3)
- Nu Sigma Nu Medical Scholarship Fund
  The Nu Sigma Nu Medical Scholarship Fund series contains three principle files: Applicants, Committee, and Funding. The Applicants file contains separate chronological folders with information on each year's applicants. The file Committee contains background information (including a list of the recipients of the scholarship through the year 1997), member correspondence, and minutes from their meetings. The file Funding contains correspondence regarding the creation of the scholarship endowment fund as well as photocopies of the front pieces of three plaques that recognized the efforts of key contributors to the fund.
  - Applicants
    - 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 3)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 3)
    - 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - 1998-1999 (Box 3)
    - Testimonials 1989 (Box 3)
  - Committee
    - Background Information 1989-1997 (contains scholarship recipient list) (Box 3)
    - Incoming Correspondence 1988-1990 (Box 3)
    - Internal Correspondence 1988-1990 (Box 3)
    - Meeting Minutes/Agendas 1988-1990 (Box 3)
    - Outgoing Correspondence 1988-1991 (Box 3)
  - Funding
    - Domino's Pizza Foundation 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - Incoming Correspondence 1989-1992 (Box 3)
    - Outgoing Correspondence 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Recognition
    - Recognition of Contributors (photocopies) (Box 3)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series contains five subseries. The subseries Class Composites contains photographs of the senior classes of the Alpha Chapter from the years 1883 to 1993, as well as additional group photographs. Many of the pictures are in oversized storage due to their large size. When not indicated otherwise, the photograph is available in the box listed on the finding aid. The subseries Individual Portraits contains photographs or drawings of Nu Sigma Nu alumni, usually taken during the height of their career. There are two unidentified men in this collection; they are housed together in one folder. The subseries Reunion and Convention Photographs contains formal and candid photographs taken at a convention in 1966 and the All-Year Reunion in 1990. The subseries Social Events contains candid pictures taken at different parties hosted by the Alpha Chapter of Nu Sigma Nu ca. 1990. These snapshots are housed in one folder and three photo albums, which were created by the members of the Alpha Chapter for their own use. In the subseries House Photographs there are pictures of the 1906 House at 1015 E. Huron.
  - Class Composites
    - 1882 Charter Members (Box 3)
    - 1883 (Box 3)
      (also oversized)
    - circa 1885-1905, 2 folders (Folder Bimu)
    - 1906 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1908 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1910 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1912 (in two pieces, fragile) (Box 3)
    - 1918 (Box 3)
    - 1921 (Box 3)
    - 1923 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1926 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1928 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1932 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1933 (Box 3)
    - 1934 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1936 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1937 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1938 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1939 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1940 (Box 3)
      (2 different photographs)
    - 1942 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1943 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1946 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1949 (Box 3)
    - 1950 (Box 3)
    - 1954 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1955 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1957 (Box 3)
    - 1958 (Box 3)
    - 1960 (Folder Bimu)
      (fragile)
    - 1961 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1962 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1963 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1964 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1965 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1966 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1967 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1968 (Box 3)
    - 1969 (Box 3)
    - 1970 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1971 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1972 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1974 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1975 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1976 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1977 (Box 3)
      (oversized)
    - 1978 (Box 3)
      (partial)
    - 1979 (Box 3)
    - 1980 (Box 3)
    - 1981 (Box 3)
    - 1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983 (Box 3)
    - 1984 (Box 3)
    - 1985 (Box 3)
    - 1990 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1991 (Folder Bimu)
    - 1993 (Folder Bimu)
    - Unidentified circa 1950s (Box 3)
  - House Photographs
    - 1906 House (1015 E. Huron) (Box 3)
  - Individual Portraits (all oversized)
    - Alexander-Edmunds (Folder Bimu)
      - Alexander, John
      - Barrett, Albert M.
      - Camp, Carl D.
      - Cowie, D. Murray
      - Cushny, Arthur R.
      - Darling, C.G.
      - Dingman, Reed O.
      - Dunphy, H. G.
      - Edmunds, Charles Wallis
    - Ford-Peterson (Folder Bimu)
      - Ford, Corydon L.
      - Gelston, L.M.
      - Haight, L. Cameron
      - Huber, G. Carl
      - Johnston, Franklin D.
      - Kahn, Edgar A.
      - Lowrey, George H.
      - Manoli, Arthur, II
      - Mayo, William J.
      - McMurrich, J. Playfair
      - Morley, George W.
      - Novy, F.G.
      - Peterson, Reuben
    - Ray-Work (Folder Bimu)
      - Ray, James H.
      - Soule, Malcolm H.
      - Walter, Will and Stuart Graves
      - Welch, William H.
      - Weller, Carl Vernon
      - Wile, Udo J.
      - Wilson, Frank N.
      - Woodburne, Russell T.
      - Work, Walter P.
    - Unidentified (2) (Folder Bimu)
  - Reunion and Convention Photographs
    - 1966 41st Biennial Convention (Box 3)
    - 1990 All-Year Reunion (Box 3)
    - Reunion snapshots circa 1990 (Box 3)
  - Social Events
    - Snapshots circa 1990 (Box 3)
    - Albums circa 1988-1991, 3 volumes (Box 4)
- Publications
  The Publications series contains formal publications of fraternity business, including yearly bulletins, event bulletins, and reports from national conventions. In addition to these occasional publications, there are four subseries: Directories, History, Nu Sigma Nu Bulletins (Softcover), and Nu Sigma Nu Bulletins (Hardcover). The subseries Directories contains geographic listings of all national Nu Sigma Nu members up to the date of publication. The History subseries contains a two-volume set that details the first fifty years of the fraternity's history. It includes an all-encompassing alumni list, organized by chapter, notes and letters addressed to the fraternity from influential Nu Sigma Nu alumni, and histories of the individual chapters as well as the national organization as a whole. It is the most comprehensive guide to the creation and development of Nu Sigma Nu. The Nu Sigma Nu Bulletins (Softcover) subseries and the Nu Sigma Nu Bulletins (Hardcover) subseries contain annual publications that detail the life of the Nu Sigma Nu fraternity of that current year. The hardcover bulletins are more formal, detailed publications, published no more than once a year and containing articles and records submitted by every active chapter of the fraternity. The softcover bulletins are smaller and less detailed. There exist several different series of publications in softcover form and some years passed without the annual publication, creating a break in the chronology.
  - Alpha of Nu Sigma Nu Annual Letter, 1904 (Box 5)
  - Alumni Bulletins 1988, 1989, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Convention Minutes/Reports 1909, 1910, 1919, 1922, 1924, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Directories
    - Geographic and Chapter Index of Nu Sigma Nu, 1905 (Box 5)
    - Geographic and Chapter Index of Nu Sigma Nu, 1909 (Box 5)
    - Geographic and Chapter Index of Nu Sigma Nu, 1915 (Box 5)
    - Geographic and Chapter Index of Nu Sigma Nu, 1917 (Box 5)
    - The Catalog of Nu Sigma Nu, 1925 (Box 5)
    - The Nu Sigma Nu Directory, 1941 (Box 5)
  - History
    - A Half Century of Nu Sigma Nu: 1882-1932 Volume 1 (Box 5)
    - A Half Century of Nu Sigma Nu: 1882-1932 Volume 2 (Box 5)
  - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletins (Softcover)
    - Ninth Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin, 1904 (Box 5)
    - Sixteenth Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin, 1909 (Box 5)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin, First Chapter Series, 1910-1911 (Box 5)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin, Second Chapter Series, 1911-1912 (Box 5)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin, Fourth Chapter Series, 1913-1914 (Box 5)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin, Tenth Chapter Series, 1919-1920 (Box 5)
    - The Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin, 1934-1935 (Box 5)
    - The Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin, Twenty-Seventh Chapter Series, 1937--38 (Box 5)
    - The Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin, Thirty-Sixth Chapter Series, 1946-1947 (Box 5)
    - The Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin, Volume XLV, Summer 1959 (Box 5)
    - The Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin, Volume LIII, Autumn 1968 (Box 5)
  - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletins (Hardcover) (Box 6)
    - Nu Sigma Nu in 1901 (Box 6)
    - Nu Sigma Nu in 1903 (Box 6)
    - Nu Sigma Nu in 1907 (Box 6)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin (Sixth Chapter Series 1915-1916) (Box 6)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin (Seventh Chapter Series 1916-1917) (Box 6)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin (Eighth Chapter Series 1917-1918) (Box 6)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin (Ninth Chapter Series 1918-1919) (Box 6)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin (Thirteenth Chapter Series 1922-1923) (Box 6)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin (Fourteenth Chapter Series 1923-1924) (Box 6)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin (Fifteenth Chapter Series 1924-1925) (Box 7)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin (Sixteenth Chapter Series 1925-1926) (Box 7)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin (Seventeenth Chapter Series 1926-1927) (Box 7)
    - Nu Sigma Nu Bulletin (Eighteenth Chapter Series 1927-1928) (Box 7)